<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The ranters principles &amp; deceits discovered and declared against, denied and disowned by us whom the world cals Quakers. With a discovery of the mistery of the crosse of Christ. And a discovery of the true light and the false, with their wayes, worships, natures, properties and effects. &amp;c. A vindication for the truth against the deceit. to clear the truth, of scandalls written for simple ones sake, that desire to know the truth as it is in Jesus.</title>
            <author>R. F. (Richard Farnworth), d. 1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85147</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F501</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E830_14</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207442</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866491</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866491</idno>
            <idno type="VID">168082</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85147)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168082)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 126:E830[14])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The ranters principles &amp; deceits discovered and declared against, denied and disowned by us whom the world cals Quakers. With a discovery of the mistery of the crosse of Christ. And a discovery of the true light and the false, with their wayes, worships, natures, properties and effects. &amp;c. A vindication for the truth against the deceit. to clear the truth, of scandalls written for simple ones sake, that desire to know the truth as it is in Jesus.</title>
                  <author>R. F. (Richard Farnworth), d. 1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 20, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert at the Black spread-Eagle at the west end of Pauls.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Preface signed: R. Forneworth.</note>
                  <note>Final leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March. 16.", "1654", "March: 16. 1654"; the final 5 in imprint date crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ranters --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168082:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Ranters Principles &amp; Deceits diſcovered and declared againſt, denied and diſowned by us whom the world cals QUAKERS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With a diſcovery of the Miſtery the Croſſe of</hi> CHRIST.</p>
            <p>And a diſcovery of the true Light and the falſe, with their wayes, worſhips, natures, properties and effects. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>A vindication for the truth againſt the deceit, to clear the truth, of Scandalls written for ſimple ones ſake, that deſire to know the truth as it is in Jeſus.</p>
            <q>Let no man deceive you with vain words, for becauſe of theſe things comes the wrath of God upon the children of diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and know you not, that the unrighteous ſhall not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit the kingdom of God, therefore be not deceived, for God will not be mocked. <bibl>Epheſ. <hi>5.3, 4, 5, 6, 1.</hi> Cor. <hi>6.9, 10.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert</hi> at the Black ſpread-Eagle at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 165<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:168082:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Leiceſterſhire</hi> from <hi>Swanington</hi> the 29. of the 6. Moneth. 1654.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>FRIENDS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>eing the deceit of the Ranters is and hath been a hinderance to many ſimple hearts from recovering the truth, and that their deceit hath opened the mouths of many to ſpeak evil of the truth, I was moved to write ſomething to lay open their deceits, falſe Reſts, and falſe liberties for the truths ſake and the ſimple ones ſake, that it may go abroad as a teſtimoniall of our deniall of them, and to be a witneſſe againſt them and their deceits, that truth may be kept clear and pure, ſo will righteouſneſſe ſhine and ſpread abroad, that wiſdom may be juſtified of her children, truth be eſtabliſhed and deceits confounded.</p>
            <p>Being in <hi>Leiceſteiſhire,</hi> and ſeeing that deceit of the Ranters there as in ſome other places to be much hinderance to honeſt hearts, keeping them back from recovering the truth, with the love of it, I have ſent this to you, that it may be a witneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them and their deceits for ever.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. Forneworth.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:168082:2"/>
            <head>The Ranters Principles &amp; deceits diſcovered and declared againſt, denied and diſowned by us whom the world calls QUAKERS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He falſe reſt and falſe liberty of the Ranters diſcovered, who be in that nature which acteth contrary to the light, with the light which never changeth are you ſeen, and with the light are you comprehended, and with the light chained and condemned, and with the light you are ſeen to be in the luſt, in the filth, and accurſed from God, who ſtands in enmity to the light, the croſſe is inward, and the true light, which light is the way to ſalvation, and bleſſed are all who walk in the light, which co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth from God, the father of lights, that with the light they may be kept out of all the pernicious wayes, which way you walk in, who are turned from the light, and that is your condemnation, the light, and the condemnation of all that hate it, and to you this is the word of the Lord, according to that in the conſcience, the light of Chriſt Jeſus, which changeth not.</p>
            <p>Remember the Angels that kept not their firſt eſtate, but left their own habitation,<note place="margin">Jude. 6, 7.</note> he hath reſerved in everlaſting chains under darkneſſe, unto the judgement of the great day, even as <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> and the cities about them, in like manner giving themſelves over to fornication, and going after ſtrange fleſh, are ſet forth for an example, ſuffering the vengeance of eternall fire, <hi>Jug.</hi> 6, 7.</p>
            <p>Mind here your types, you that have caſt the pure law of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind your backs, and have turned the grace of God into wantonneſſe, here is your character, look to your ſelves, you that have not kept your habitation with God, when once you were enlightened with the pure light, after ſo many troubles, ſorrows, fears, and tears, and watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, when the wrath of God was revealed againſt ſin and ungodlineſs in you, and the pure law was ſet up, and the judgement within you, to have freed you from ſin, and from puniſhment eternally, had you kept in the ſtrait way, and ſtood in the counſell of God, that judgement might have been brought forth into victory, and the pure ſeed have been borne up, to have ſaved you from ſin, but not abiding in the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, you have cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cified the Son afreſh, and put him to open ſhame,<note place="margin">Col. 3.1, 2, 3. Eph 5.3, 4, 5, 6, 11, 12.</note> and vo is your portion, you did run well, but you have loſt the right way, and are turned into the pathes of darkneſſe again, and you act in darkneſſe, and brings forth the fruits of unrighteouſneſſe, and are become ſervants of ſin. Remember your type, <hi>Judas</hi> likewiſe, who had
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:168082:3"/>received part of his miniſtry,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.16. John. 8.34.</note> and after betrayed the Lord of glory for ſelf ends, and to have the love and friendſhip of the world, but wo was his portion, and when he knew what he had done, he went and hanged himſelf, and his caſe is yours, who have betrayed the light of God in you, and the union with it, though it was in wrath to the ſeed of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, when your ſenſes are opened again, you ſhall ſee the miſery and the wofull eſtate and condition that you are in, and how you have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed Chriſt with a kiſſe, to deliver him into the hands of ſinners, and ſo the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tneſſe alſo lyes ſlain in you, that ſhould witneſſe and give ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence againſt ſin, but the Lord will find you out, and give you your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.5, 6, 7, 8, 9. 2. Pet. 2.11, 12, 13, 14. 2. Pet. 2.17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23. Mat. 24.50, 51.</note> you that have fed your ſelves with conceits and imaginations, from the diſcovery of the light to the ſeed, and your ſubtile wiſdomes having intruded into the room thereof, and ſo you have got into the liberty of the fleſh, and can rant and ſwagger in wickedneſſe, and ſay you are free, but it is but the fleſh that is at liberty, and that muſt be curſed, and all that follow your pernicious wayes, by reaſon of whom, the way of truth is evil ſpoken of, but you are accurſed with a curſe that is joined with the ſerpent again, you ſhall ſee him whom you have pierced, and mourn bitterly, and as <hi>Eſau</hi> did ſeek the bleſſing again with tears, but ſhall not find it, but be caſt into utter darkneſſe, where ſhall be weeping, and wailing, and gnaſhing of teeth.</p>
            <p>I know many of you were once tender and ſimple hearted, and did make conſcience of your wayes, and were zealous for the truth, and did practiſe what was made known in ſome meaſure, and were under the ſenſe of the wrath of God againſt ſin, and the witneſſe did ariſe to curſe the ſeed of the ſerpent, and then you apprehended God to be an angry God, and ſo is he ſtill againſt ſin, and will not ſuffer it to go unpuniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but that was bitter to the fleſhly part, but it had been good for you, if you had continued under the croſſe, in the executing of the righteous judgement of God upon the ſerpent in you, for in the end it would have been ſweet, when you had eaten the paſſeover, to have came to the hidden name, but not abiding under the wrath, the light vain mind is got up in you, and the fleſh is at eaſe, but wo to all careleſs ones that are at eaſe in Sion,<note place="margin">Rev. 3.12. Rev. 22.9. Rev. 21.27.</note> ſo ſoon as the pure law did break out in force, and give in ſome refreſhment to the ſeed in priſon, and the love and joy did ſpring into the impriſoned ſeed, from him who lives out of time, to refreſh that which is captivated by that which lives in times, and time, and ſo the will turned into the conceiving of ſomething from what was made out to the ſeed, and the faln wiſdom joined with the corrupt will, and got liberty from under the croſs, and the Divell he wrought ſtrongly upon the imaginations, and ſo ſought to comprehend the light, and drew a vail over the heart, and there he acted in the miſtery of the iniquity after the pure were vailed, and he brought all into queſtion, and pleaded for liberty to the fleſh, through his workings upon the imaginations, and the comprehenſions by carnall reaſon, and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:168082:3"/>the faln wiſdom joining to conceive and comprehend, to have all at command, and be as God, knowing good and evil, and now ſaith the Divell, all is good, and there is nothing evil, but as thou conceiveſt it to be ſo, and thou art brought into the knowledge of this, that is, all good, and it was but thy weakneſſe to think that there was any thing evil; now thou art the ſon of God, and thou knoweſt it, all is thine, take thy liberty, and rejoyce, let thy heart be merry, uſe all things in righteouſneſſe, and there is no ſin in them, thou haſt been ſo crittick, that thou couldſt ſcarce look chearfully, or partake of any thing that was for thy comfort, but now thou art a ſon, and thou ſeeſt how thou haſt been kept from thy l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>berty meerly through thy conceits and appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l, and an angry God againſt ſin, and fear leaſt thou ſhouldeſt go into a place thou calleſt hell, but ſaith he, now thou maiſt ſee it was but the weak and low apprehenſions in thoſe things, there is neither hell nor Divell, nor any ſuch thing, but what as was in thee, and thou haſt got through thoſe conceits now rejoyce and be merry, and take thy pleaſure, uſe thy freedom, thou art a ſon, and if a ſon, then an heir, and thou maiſt laugh the heathen to ſcorn, poor fooles, that they ſhould ſo deprive themſelves of their liberty and freedom as they do, and be bound ſo to falſe conceits as they are, becauſe that their judgements are not rightly informed, to know all things to be good, and this which they call ſin, to be but a conceit, and that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they knew their freedom, they might rejoyce and he glad. &amp;c. and thus the Devill he works ſtrongly upon the imaginations, when the light breakes forth, and the love comes to be made manifeſt to the ſeed in priſon, not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biding in the croſſe, the will is ſeeking to comprehend and get out from under the judgement, and here Satan doth delude and deceive under fair colours, like an angell of light, and leads out into fleſhly love; fleſhly joy, fleſhly liberty, and fleſhly pleaſures; and calls all good, and calleth that a freedom by the ſon, but it is but by the ſon of perdition; that doth exalt himſelf above all that is called God, and that liberty which he leads into, is a falſe liberty and thou ſhalt find it, whoever thou art that takes his counſell, after that the light do ariſe in thee, then he uſeth all his devices to deceive withall, which before were not known, afterwards comes to be made known, and wo to them that turn out of the ſtrait way, and the daily croſſe, to ſeek eaſe to the fleſh, there they took counſell of the Devill, and he will work them into ſuch a ſtrong combination with the powers of darkneſſe, that they ſhall find that of the Apoſtle to be true, thoſe that were once enlightened, and have taſted of the good word of God, and the powers of the world to come, if they ſhall fall away, to renew then again to repentance, they crucify to themſelves the ſon of God afreſh, and put him to an open ſhame, and wo is thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> portion,<note place="margin">Heb. 6.4, 5, 6, 7, 8.</note> for the earth that drinketh in the rain that cometh oft upon it, and bringeth forth herbs meet for them, by whom it is dreſſed, receiveth bleſſing from God, ſo do they that abide
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:168082:4"/>in the teaching and counſell of God, who works them into a fruitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to bring praiſe to his name, to receive his bleſſing, which is as the dew of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>aven, to water, nouriſh, and comfort their ſouls, but that nature which is contrary to the light, and all that go out of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of God, and the daily croſſe, turneth into the crooked paths of fleſhly delights and pleaſures, and diſhonoureth the Lord, and is as the ground that beareth nothing but thornes, and is rejected, and is nigh unto curſing and burning, and ſo are they who turn the grace of God into wantoneſſe, and laſciviouſneſſe, and will not abide the fire, and the ſword, to c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t down the thorny nature, and the fleſhly corrupt heart, and to burn the earth, and place of the ſerpents abode in them, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt they know the eternall fire, and vengeance of God to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed from heaven, for they who ſin wilfully after that they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the knowledge of the truth, there remains no more ſacrifice for ſin, but a fearfull looking for of judgement, and fiery indignation of the Lord, which ſhall devour the adverſaries. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.4. to the 8.2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.6, 7, 8, 9. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.26, 27.</p>
            <p>Look to your ſelves all Ranters and Libertines, who turns the grace of God into wantoneſſe, the Devill he hath deceived you, and you ſeek to deceive others, preaching to them liberty, when you your ſelves are the ſervants of ſin, but wo and miſery is your portion, yet the Lord may pluck ſome as brands out of the fire, that they may be witneſſes for the truth, againſt the deceits to forewarn all of that dangerous way, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Divell lyeth in wait to deceive if it were poſſible the very elect, but for the elects ſake doth the Lord diſcover your deceits, and falſe light, Liberties, Reſts, and pleaſures, which you live and take delight and pleaſure in, wo is your portion, for the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it, and this I teſtify unto you, from the word of the Lord.</p>
            <p>But you may object and ſay,<note place="margin">Object. Gal. 5.1. Rom. 14.14. 2. Cor. 5.18.</note> did not the Apoſtle ſay, ſtand faſt in tnac liberty, wherewith Chriſt hath ſee you free, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.1. and he ſaid all things are lawfull for me, but all things are not expedient, and I know and am perſwaded by the Lord Ieſus, that there is nothing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean of it ſelf, but to him that eſteemeth it to be unclean, to him it is unclean, and to the pure all things are p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re, and all things are of God, who hath reconciled us to himſelf, by Ieſus Chriſt, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I anſwer,<note place="margin">Anſ.</note> that the liberty which Chriſt parchaſeth to and for his, is a liberty and freedom from ſin, and he that ſaith he is in Chriſt, ought to walk as he alſo walked. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.4, 5, 6. who was a pattern and an example for all his to follow,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 2.4, 5, 6. 2. Pet. 3. chap to the end.</note> but who lives in the fleſh, and have their liberty in the pleaſures, and delights thereof, and are in the luſt, are out of the light, and ſo out of Chriſt, an I know no freedom by the ſon, but are in the pathes that leads to deſtruction, and are ſervant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to ſin, and lives in uncleaneſſe and filthineſſe of the fleſh, which neither Chriſt nor the Apoſtles did uſe, but doth forbid ſuch practiſe and fleſhly liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as you uſe, who are in uncleaneſſe, and are ſervants of Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:168082:4"/>2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 13. to the end, with the light are you ſeen, &amp; comprehended, and with the light condemned.</p>
            <p>And where he ſaid all things were lawfull to him, he was ſpeaking of meats, and ſuch like, but he did no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> any liberty to the fleſh,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.16. 1 Ioh. 3.6, 7, 8. v.</note> but ſaid, ſhall we continue in ſin that grace may abound, God forbid, know ye not ſaith he, that they which commit ſin are the ſervants of ſin, and ſo ſerveth the Devill. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.16. 1 <hi>Job.</hi> 3.6, 7, 8. And thirdly where he ſaith, I know and am perſwaded by the Lord Ieſus, that there is nothing unclean ot it ſelf, but to him that eſteemeth it to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean, it is ſo, but he is not ſpeaking of ſin nor fleſhly liberty, but to tender conſciences in that place, and his care was ſo tender ever them that were in a ſcrupling condition about the unlawfulneſſe of eating all meats, and ſuch like. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. chap. that he would not have a weak brother grieved, for ſaith he, if thy brother be offended with thy meat, which he had been ſpeaking of the pureneſſe and lawfulneſſe of it, as it came out of the covenant from God, yet ſaith he, if he be grieved, now walkeſt thou not charitably, deſtroy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot him with thy meat, for whom Chriſt died, let not then your good be evil ſpoken of, for the kingdom of God is nor meat nor drink, but righteouſneſſe and peace, and joy in the holy Ghoſt, for he that in theſe things ſerveth Chriſt, is acceptable to God, and approved of men, let us therefore follow after thoſe things which make for peace, and things wherewith o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> may edify another. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. from the 14. verſe, where he is ſpeaking of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>awfulneſſe and purity of all things as they are in God, and ſo on to the end, he ſheweth how they are, and in what manner to be uſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, but you that follow after unrighteouſneſſe, to ſatisfy your fleſhly luſts and pleaſures, are not in the light, nor the kingdom of God, but out of the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght, and in that nature which is accurſed from God and you who are turned from the light, and live in unrighteouſneſſe, you are the very enemies of all purity, and lives in uncleaneſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, and muſt be torn ented with the wrath of God, and to the light in all your conſcience ſhall this be wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed, and where he ſaith, All things are of God, he is ſpeaking to them that were born of God, who abode in the light, and were new creatures, the old things were paſſed away, and the old luſts, and old naturall corruptions, and they were new creatures, and ſo redeemed into purity with God, and in covenant with him, and they knew no man in the fleſhly union, wherefore ſaith he, henceforth we know no man after the fleſh, yea though we have known Chriſt after the fleſh, yet henceforth know we him ſo no more, therefore ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>h <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to others that were in the light, as well as them,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.16, 17, 18.</note> that were in the life and power of truth, if any man be in Chriſt, he is a n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w creature, but you cannot ſay ſo in truth, who lives in the unity of the world, and in the old na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, he that is in the new nature, all things that were from the old root of corruption, is paſſed away in him, and all things become new, and that is the all things which the Apoſtle there ſpeaks of, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:168082:5"/>16, 17, 18. All things that are in the new nature are pure, and he that is born of God is pure, and one in that nature, and he is coined before the world was, and before the corruptions, or filthineſſe of the fleſh was, and he ſees all things in God to be pure and good, and from one root, and all things to be unpure and unclean that is of the evil root, and ſo that which proceeds from the fountain of corruption to be of the Divell, and if any man have an car, let him hear what the ſpirit ſaith, for the ſecrets of the Lord are with them that fear him, here with that light which never changeth are you all ſeen and comprehended, who art turned out of the light,<note place="margin">Iam. 3.11. to the end.</note> and with the light chained and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emned, and laſtly to the pure all things are pure, none is pure but God, the father of ſpirits without Lord Ieſus Chriſt and he that is born of God the father and the ſon, they are all one, and he that is ſanctified by the Son, he is made clean in and by the divine power of righteouneſſe, and ye are clean, through the word ſaith Ieſus Chriſt, and I am in you, and you are in me, and all things that the Father hath are mine, and the holy Ghoſt ſhall take of mine, and ſhew unto you all that are in covenant with God, are made pure with the bloud of the Lamb, and are redeemed to purity again, and all things that comes out of the covenant from God, to them is pure, his love, is pure without any mixture of the love of the world, for that is unpure, and full of luſt, and ſelf-ends, but the love of God is pure, and his wiſdom is pure, pure love, pure heart, pure peace, comfort, and joy in the holy Ghoſt, all the makings forth of God to the ſoul is pure, and all the works of God in themſelves as they are wrought in the ſoul are pure, but the Divell would defile the work, and ſow in his ſeed, if he be not watched over, and all his works are evil, ſuch is his nameſuch is his nature, and his ſeed is corrupt, and he acteth and guideth it, and raiſeth it up by the power of darkneſſe, to oppoſe the good ſeed which is of God, and is acted and guided, and raiſed up by the power of God in thoſe that are obedient to the commands of the ſpirit of truth, and quenches not the motions of it, it works into purity and alſo into unity with the divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and reconciliation with the father and the ſon, and in that unity things are pure, but who lives in the luſt, the old nature and the fall, know it not, for great is the miſtery of godlineſſe, from whence all pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity ſprings, and bleſſed are they who are reconciled to God, and under the dominion and government of the ſpirit of truth, where the pure life, and the heavenly food is, and ſpirituall lawes ſtatutes and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances are to walk in, and the Lord God and the Lamb, the light and glory of the ſpirituall kingdom, where all variecies is in their purity; but who are yet reconciled to God, are under the dominion of the Prince of darkneſs, and ſucks poiſon from the corrupt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oor, and ſo feeds the fleſh, and wallowes in the mire and luſt of their own conceivings, inventions and fleſhly imaginations, and ſo are under the curfe and wrath of the almighty, but God hath not called us to uncleaneſs, but to holineſs, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:168082:5"/>I know she vain light mind, and the careleſſe dark ſpring will ſay,<note place="margin">Object.</note> let, the ſeed of the ſerpent be accurſed, and let it be damned, ſo that God ſave his own, I care not what he doth with me, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But be thou aſſured and know this,<note place="margin">Anſ.</note> that as the ſeed of the ſerpent is accurſed from God, he that is joined to the ſeed of the ſerpent is one, and body and ſoul and all is polluted by reaſon of ſin, and except thou know thy redemption by the power of the Lord to ſeparate the ſeed of the ſerpent and thou aſunder, and to un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te thee to the power of truth, thou wilt be accurſed from God both ſoul and body, and all that is one with the ſerpent, and be puniſhed with everlaſting deſtruction from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lord, and the preſence of the holy Angels, for as they did not like to retain God in their knowledge, God gave them over to 2 reprobate mind, to work all uncleaneſſe with greedineſſe,<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 1.7, 8. Rom. 1.18, 29.</note> and when they knew God, they glorifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d him not as God, but became vain in their imaginations, and their fooliſih hearts were darkened, for the miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of iniquity doth work there ſtrongly with all deceiveableneſſe of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe in them that periſh, becauſe they received not the love of the truth, that they might be ſaved, and for this cauſe God ſhall ſend them ſtrong deluſions that they ſhould believe a lye, that they all might be damned who believed not the truth, but had pleaſure in unrighteouſneſſe. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12.</p>
            <p>Thou maiſt ſay that there is no evil nor no Divell,<note place="margin">Object. Anſ.</note> but thou ſhalt knew that there is a Divell and a hell, and a root from whence all evil doth proceed, and though thou ſaiſt it is but a conceit, yet be ſure. O vain man; whatſoever thou art, God will be aveanged of thee, and ſuffer the tormented to plague thee for thy ſpirituall wickedneſſe, blaſphemy and deſpight to the ſpirit of grace, for all ſins and blaſphemies againſt men ſhall be forgiven, but the ſin againſt the holy Ghoſt, which is to ſin wilfully after grace received, and to ſpeak evil of the power of truth, that ſin ſhall never be forgiven, neither in this world nor in that which is to come.</p>
            <p>Thou maiſt ſay it is but a conceit to tell of ſin and the Divell,<note place="margin">Object. Anſ.</note> but it is but a deceit which tells thee there is none, and ſo thou art ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up in uncleaneſſe, and the cuſtome of ſin taketh away the conſcience of ſinning, and thou art ſeared and makes no conſcience of what thou doſt, but thou maiſt as well ſay, it is but a conceit to ſay, the Sun is not the Sun, it is but a conceit to think ſo, as to ſay there is no ſin nor Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell, but good and evil are all alike &amp;c. But will any who are endued with naturall knowledge believe thee, if thou ſaiſt there is neither Sun nor Moon, night nor day, they are all alike, only they conceive it to be day and night, Sun-light and Moon-light, but it is but their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit that they have of theſe things; But is it ſo, becauſe thou ſayeſt ſo, will not the very naturall man that hath his naturall ſight and knowledge of thoſe things, tell thee thou art a lyar, and ſpeakes but only thy conceits, and fleſhly conceivings, and carnall inventions, but
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:168082:6"/>it is vain for thee to deceive one that hath his eyes in his head, in thoſe things.</p>
            <p>But if it were to a naturall blind man, that never ſaw any of theſe, but were born blind, thou mighteſt deceive him in thoſe things ſoon, to tell him there is neither night nor day, Sun nor Moon, but as mens conceits carrieth them forth to conceive of theſe things, according to their low apprehenſions that they have of thoſe things, thou mighteſt deceive a blind man in thoſe things, becauſe that he never ſaw them, but only as he heard others ſpeak of them, but he that ſeeth and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth or thoſe things, he will tell thee thou art a fool to labour to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade him to believe thy conceits, when he ſeeth it to the contrary evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently before his eyes.</p>
            <p>So on the contrary, to ſay there is neither God nor Divell, heaven nor hell, nor ſin, nor ſorrow, will any believe thee that knows thoſe things, whoſe eyes are in his head hath evidently ſeen the nature and property of theſe, he that is born again, and enlightened by the ſpirit of Jeſus Chriſt, knows that thou art a lyar, to ſay that good and evil, righteouſneſſe and unrigteouſneſſe, is all one, and proceeds from one root, it is but only their low apprehenſions and conceits to think other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, as thou ſayeſt, but thy ſaying is falſe.</p>
            <p>And I teſtify againſt thee that ſayeth ſo, be what thou wilt, or who thou wilt, thou art guided by a lying ſpirit, and art of thy father the Divell, who was a lyar from the beginning, and the father of it, <hi>Joh.</hi> 8. 44. the Divell that deceived thee was a lyar from the beginning, and he hath ſince the beginning got into thy heart, and hath been work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon thy imaginations, and drawn thee out into conceits, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall imaginations of things, through the wiles and craftineſſe of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveableneſſe, whereby he hath plunged thee into the pit of inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and divinations of thy own brain, but thou art ſhut out of the truth, and art blind and ignorant altogether of unfolding the divine and heavenly myſtery, and art kept in the fountain of filthineſſe, of the Divells ſuggeſtions, who acteth thee by the power of darkneſſe, and caſts a miſt before thy eyes, the eyes of thy underſtanding, that thou ſhouldſt be blind, and groap by thy faln wiſdom, and the knowledge in the hiſtory, but art yet in wickedneſſe, and deep in the miſtery of iniquity, and knoweſt nothing but the evil it ſelf, and calls that good, but the wo is to thee that doſt ſo, for thou art blinded by ſeeking to comprehend the light by thy carnall wiſdom, thou mayeſt as well ſeek to comprehend the Sun in thy band, for light ſhineth in darkneſſe, but darkneſſe comprehends it not.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.5.</note> This then is the meſſage, that God is light,<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.5,</note> and in him is no darkneſſe at all, if we ſay we have fellowſhip with him, and walk in darkneſſe, we lye, and do not the truth, but if we walk in the light as he is in the light, we have fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip one with another,<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.5, 6, 7</note> and the bloud of Ieſus Chriſt his ſon cleanſeth us from all ſin, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.5, 6, 7, he that dwelleth in God, dwelleth in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:168082:6"/>light, but he that is out of God, is in darkneſſe, and walketh in crook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed paths, that leads to deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Therefore I ſay unto you, who deſire to fear the Lord, as <hi>John</hi> ſaid to the brethren, Little children, let no man deceive you, he that doth righteouſneſſe is righteous, even as he is righteous, but he that doth not righteouſneſſe, is not of God, neither he that loveth not his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in this the children of God are made manifeſt,<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 3.9, 10.</note> and the children of the Divell. 1. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.9, 18.</p>
            <p>Here is two ſeeds acted by two powers, and receiveth ſtrength from two roots, the ſeed of God acted by the power of God, and all who are in unity with that ſeed, are crucified to the world, and dead to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe, Chriſt being made manifeſt, to deſtroy the works of the Divell, who is the bright &amp; morning ſtar, I am the root and off-ſpring of <hi>David; Rev.</hi> 22.16. ſaith Jeſus Chriſt, and he that is unjuſt, let him be uniuſt ſtill, and he that is ſaithy, let him be filthy ſtill, there is the evil ſeed, but he that, is righteous, let him be righteous ſtill, and he that is holy, let him be holy ſtill, there is the good ſeed, and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe ſpringeth from one root, and is of God, and all who act in righteouſneſſe, who are acted and guided by the divine power of God, are one, and are in covenant with God; but all unrighteouſneſſe doth ſpring from another root,<note place="margin">Rev. 22.10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15. Iſa. 5.22, 23, 24, Rev. 22.16, 17. Iſa. 28.13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19.</note> and thoſe who are of unrighteouſneſſe are of the ſeed of the ſerpent, and are acted and guided by the power of the Divell, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15. and I witneſſe the ſame with the Scriptures by experience, that good and evil it from two roots, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct, and two powers; therefore be not deceived, for God will not be mocked. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.14, 15. <hi>Act.</hi> 26.28. <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.4. <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.10, 11, 12, 13, 14. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.11, 12. to the end of the chapter. You who are of the unrighteouſneſſe, and of the ſeed of the ſerpent are one, and all in covenant with the Divell, and have made a covenant with death and Hell, that the Scriptures maybe fulfilled. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.15.28 chap. 1. 2. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 13, 24.</p>
            <p>But you can deceive none but ſuch as are of the ſame ſeed of evil do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers with you, who are of the ſerpent, and lives in the fall, and the luſt of the fleſh, forſaking the fountain of living mercies, to delight in lying vanities; but the ſeed of God is ſpringing up, and begin to grow, and righteouſneſſe will be a terrour to unrighteouſneſſe, and the ſeed of God will be a torment to the ſeed; at the ſerpent, and the Lord ruling in his Saints, will be a terrour to the heathen; Howl ye ſerpents, and all ye dragons, for you will be found out, and have the vialle of wrath and indignation poured forth upon you, howl ye luſtfull ones, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in unrighteouſneſſe, the Lord will be avenged of you,<note place="margin">Iſa. 1.24. Iſa. 3.11.</note> all ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance is mine, all I will repay ſaith the Lord, ſury to mine adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, you would have two kingdoms, but <hi>Eſaus</hi> dominion is yours, and the hatred of God it to you all, who delight in unrighteouſneſſe, and and ye ſhall deſire to ſee one of the daies of the ſon of man, out ſhall not,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:168082:7"/>or the mouth of the Lord of hoſts hath ſpoken it, and this declare I unto you from the word of the Lord.</p>
            <p>The miſtery of the croſſe of Chriſt, and the law in the heart, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king hold upon ſin and all unrighteouſneſſe, to cut it down, and caſt it out, through the working of the divine power of God in Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde.</p>
            <p>The croſſe is inward,<note place="margin">Ioh. 16.7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, v. Luk. 9.23, 24, 25, 26. 1 Cor. 1.17, 18. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 6.14.</note> to the cutting down of ſin and uncleaneſſe within, the pure light of God, which convinceth of ſin and evil, and witneſſeth againſt all the branching forth of the unrighteous power of darkneſſe in man, when his mind, will and affections would run forth into the world, to conceive ſome comfort to himſelf, out of die viſible objects, his heart is ſoon taken through the outgoing of his eye, with the things of the world, and he transformes the very image of what part of the creation ſoever his eye was out after, and ſets it up in his heart; if it be a houſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> field, horſe, oxe, or any other creature, he is taken with beauty or riches, and ſo his heart is ſtoln away into the earth, and he ſets his affections on the things, below God, and his will falls down to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip ſilver and gold, and ſuch like things, making them his Gods, to delight himſelf in, and when his heart is running out after the love and honour of the world, there is a principle of purity within tells him, all is but vanity, and this calls for equity, equity to take of oppreſſion and cruelty, but the luſtfull proud nature croſſeth that principle of purity, and draweth the heart after vanity, when the Divell bears rule in the heart, working into the miſtery of the iniqnity, but that of purity which calls for equity, ſtill cryeth out, and tells man, all is but vanity, and calls and cryes in his heart for purity, and to ſet up truth and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe; and to do to all men as he would be done by, for that is the Law and the Prophets, and to love God with all his heart, and his neighbour as himſelf, and to give over folly and vanity, this is the croſſe to iniquity, which calleth and cryeth for juſtice and equity, and love and pity, let that be heard and obeyed in you, and it will ſhut out jollity, and cut off vanity, and work into unity with that which calleth for purity, and croſſe the luſtfull proud nature, that hardneſs of heart may not rule over juſtice and equity. Conſider oh man, that thou art mortall, and muſt return to duſt, and be caſt into torment and burning, if thou wilt not give ear to the cry of the poor, that which is pure in thee, that it may work thee into charity, and ſhew thee the way that leads to eternity, and cut of oppreſſion and tyranny, that diligence may rule in thee, that thy luſts may be ſlain, that would break the bonds of amity, the pure light will witneſs againſt the dark nature in thee, and ſtrike at the root of all enmity, to reconcile thy ſoul unto God, in yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the pure law of love, and the divine power of purity, in thee, and ſo circumciſe thy heart, and cut off the evil nature which hinders thy, ſoul of the unity; ſo will the righteous law kill ſin in thee, and give thee knowledge of the true way that leadeth to life, joy and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:168082:7"/>comfort in yielding obedience to the principle of purity in thee, heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to that which checks thee for running into folly and van<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ity, and it will croſſe thy mind, will, and affections,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.19. 2 Cor. 4.6, 7. Pro. 20.27.</note> that runs out after carnality and ſo ſearch thy heart, and turn thee out of the iniquity, and guide and lead thee into holyneſſe and purity, in walking up to God, in the right way that leadeth to the divinity with Chriſt, I am the way, the truth, and the life, and no man cometh to the father but by me, know Chriſt the way in you, to lead out of darkneſs into the light of purity, Chriſt is the light, and Chriſt is the way, and he comes to ſet up his judgement within, and to reveal wrath againſt ſin, and to break the peace of the carnall mind, and to draw under judgement all the firſt birth,<note place="margin">Ioh. 9.39. 1 Cor. 1.19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 24, 25. Col. 2.13.14. Eph. 2.11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16,</note> both the love of the world, the wiſdom of the fleſh, and carnall reaſon, and lead that into the pit of confuſion, to ſlay the enmity by the execution of the righteous judgement upon the unjuſt nature, that he may pour forth fury upon the head of the wicked, and ſlay that which croſseth purity, and oppoſeth the work of redemption, as man doth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the comings in of wrath, to the wrathfull nature, to cut it down, and burn it up, that the good ſeed may hare room to grow in man, and make man fruitfull to God, in joining with the ſlayer of ſin, that the world, or the creature man may be ſaved by the power of the Lord, which doth redeem the ſoul, and unite both ſoul and body to God, that they may be reconciled by the death of the croſs in the myſtery, to praiſe and glorify God in ſincerity, and in integrity.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:168082:8"/>
               <head>The true light, and the falſe, with their waies, worſhips, natures, properties, and effects.</head>
               <p>This then is the meſſage that we have received, to declare unto you, that God is light and in him is no darkneſſe at all, and that every good and perfect gift is from above, and cometh from the father of lights, with whom is no variable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,<note place="margin">Iam. 1.17, 18. 1 Pet. 1.22. Rom. 11.16. Eph. 5.1, 2. Eph. 2.8, 9, 10.</note> neither ſhaddow of turning, for of his own will begat he us, that we ſhould be a kind of firſt fruits of his creatures, being born again, and children of the light, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.22. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.16. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.1, 2.</p>
               <p>God is the fountain of all good, and of mans ſalvation, and happineſſe, and God is pure, his waies, words, works and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips are pure and holy, and this holy God doth inhabit in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity, and dwelleth in purity, in himſelf, and none can ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to come near him in their ſins, nor by their faln wiſdom, none knowes him but thoſe that are born again, and waſhed and cleanſed (not in his purity) therefore as he that hath called you is holy,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.14. 1 Pet. 1.15, 16.</note> ſo be ye holy in all manner of conversation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is written, be ye holy as I am holy, for holineſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh mine houſe for ever, as God is pure and holy, ſo the light that proceedeth and cometh forth from God is pure and holy, and ſtands out of all apprehenſions, and comprehenſions of man, by his faln wiſdom, and ſo ſees all mans devices, his deceits, and falſe waies, and falſe worſhips, and this pure light that doth proceed and come forth from God which is pure, and perfect, it convinceth man of all the deceits of his heart, and of all his devices, and deceiveableneſſe, and of all his falſe waies of worſhip, and ſheweth him his tranſgreſſions, and convinceth him of unrighteouſneſſe and infidelity, and all manner of evil whatſoever, and calleth him out of the waies and works of darkneſſe, into unity with this pure light, and leads him into the way of peace and ſalvation, in obedience to it, to worſhip God in purity, even in ſpirit, and in the life and power of truth,<note place="margin">Ioh. 16.25, 26, 17, 28. Ioh. 12.35, 36.</note> this light is from the fountain of lights, it is not a conceited thing, that is conceived in the brain, but it is the light of life, and is not to be found in books nor learning with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, it gathers out of all books without, to reading the book of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:168082:8"/>life, within; this light opens all Scriptures,<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 5.8, 9, 10, 11. Ioh. 17.23, 14.</note> and Ieads man out of the fall, up to God, the fountain &amp; father of lights, this is the true light, &amp; leadeth into life eternall, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.12, 13. <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.10.</p>
               <p>But the naturall men know it not by their naturall learning, at ſtudies, at univerſities, that is but a borrowed or falſe light, that leads them into books and ſtudies, to find out the truth by their carnall wiſdom, which is gathered up from the ſerpent, and is accurſed from God, and that faln wiſdom, and man that lives by conceivings, and comprehenſion, and catching of truthes in the nation, to ſpeak of, and ſell for mony, it is earthly, carnall, and diveliſh,<note place="margin">Iam. 3.15, 16.</note> and he that is joined to that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine wiſdom, is one with it, in the ſame nature, and ſets up a way of worſhip, that ſtands in the carnall conceivings of his own brain, in imitation from them who lived in the life and power of truth, and his miniſtry that is of the ſeed of the ſerpent, ſtands in his own will, and ſo learns his naturall tongues, and ſo would be a judge of ſpirituall things, by his naturall learning, and trades out of books, and the conceivings of his own brain, to ſell his divinations at a great rate, and calIs them his ſpirituall things, when he is in his carnall corrupt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 13, 14. 2 Cor. 10.4, 5. 2 Pet. 1.19, 20, 21. Ioh. 28.7, 8, to the 22. Iſa. 30. Ier. 23.29, 30, 31, 32. Iſa. 5.20. Mat. 23.24, 25. Ioh. 8.12.</note> and the naturall man knows not the things of the ſpirit God, for they are fooliſhneſſe to him, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.14, 15.</p>
               <p>And that is a falſe light that leads the minds of men out into conceivings and imaginations, and to gather up knowledge out of old authours, or books without them, and that light which is borrowed from without, and gathered into the brain, through the conceivings and imaginations, leads the mind, will, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections out, after pride, and oppreſſion, ſelf-love, and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the world, and the like, and it conceives that to be good alſo, and all to be evil that croſſeth his knowledge in his carnall conceivings, but the light that leads out into ſuch things is a falſe light, &amp; a blind guide, and he that is guided &amp; led by ſuch a falſe light, he knows not the true light, which leadeth out of all books and hiſtories, into the life, in the myſtery, and leads out of pride into humility, out of covetcuſneſſe, into compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onateneſſe, &amp; fruits of that nature: but the light is in the world, and the world knoweth it not, the true light, which ſees all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits, and comprehends all <hi>Babylons</hi> wayes, works, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, and ſees where the beaſt and falſe prophet is, and the mother of harlots, with their ſorceries and divinations, and the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:168082:9"/>cup of their fornications, whereby they deceive the nations, but God will bring them all into contempt, and make them aſhamed of their deceits and deceiveableneſſe, for the light is riſen and ariſing, that will lay open all their abominations, and give them the cup of fury, and make <hi>Babylons</hi> merchants and craftſmen ſick with amazement, and with aſtoniſhment, at the calamity that is to come upon them, now read where you are, he that hath an ear to hear, let him hear what the ſpirit ſaith. <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.3, 4, 5. to the 18.</p>
               <p>The true light now ſhineth in darkneſſe, but darkneſſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendeth it not.</p>
               <p>Even that light which is pure and perfect, which proceeds and cometh from God, the father of lights, but dark mindes knowes it not, but walks in darkneſſe, diſobeying the light, and there is their condemnation, the diſobedience to the light, where it is in meaſure made manifeſt. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.19, 20, 21. God is ſupernaturall, and this light proceeds and comes from him, which is the true light, that convinceth of ſin, and exerciſeth the pure ſenſes, working in the conſcience, to bring men up to God, into that which is eternall, out of corruptions into purity, and unity with the divinity, to reconcile them to have fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with the father and the Son, and receive joy and comfort from the holy Ghoſt, to praiſe and glorify God in the ſpirit, who ſendeth the ſpirit of his Son into their hearts,<note place="margin">Ioh. 16.13, 14, 15. Ioh. 14.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, 27. Ioh. 15.1, 2, 3.</note> to adminiſter true comfort to the ſoul, and this miniſtry ſtandeth not in the will of man, nor in the wiſdom of the fleſh, but in the power of God, and in demonſtration of the ſpirit, baptizing with the Holy Ghoſt, into the holy union, to drink and receive joy and comfort from the Lord Jeſus, the ſpirituall vine, and theſe fruits and effects proceeds from the true light, that worketh power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully in the ſpirituall miniſtration, drawing ſouls out of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe into light, out of corruptions into purity, out of the falſe wayes and falſe worſhips, into the true way that leadeth into life eternall, where the miſtery of faith is held in a pure conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and there is no uncleaneſſe where this is fulfilled: for God the fountain of light is pure, and of purer eyes then to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold iniquity, and he ſends this light, to enlighten the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, and draw up ſouls to God, out of the fall into the pure life again, and this gift is perfect, that cometh from God to draw ſouls up into perfection, and into the powrings forth of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:168082:9"/>love, to rejoyce in him for ever. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. to the 9. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. 23, 24, to the end. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 3, 4.</p>
               <p>But naturall men, that have but learned their naturall things, of Greek, Latine, and Hebrew? which the naturall man may eaſily do, and yet be an enemy to God, and to his own ſoul, for all his naturall learning and languages, and be ignorant of God, for the naturall man knowes him not, and he is a very naturall indeed, that ſaith this pure light of God which doth convince of ſin, and uncleaneſſe is a naturall light, he that ſaith ſo, is a dim light, and blind guide indeed, and knowes not God.</p>
               <p>For this light that reproves for ſin in the conſcience is a divine principle, and was with the Father in the beginning, but in due time he manifeſts himſelf by it, to the view of the minds and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings of men, to let them ſee into their ſelves, that they are all gentiles, in their firſt nature, and ſinners, and are under the curſe and wrath of God, and no reconciliation can be made, whilſt the ſeed of the ſerpent is head, unbruiſed in them, &amp; had not this come forth from God, to give man a diſcovery of his heart, he had not known ſin, but the light coming and appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in him, he ſees himſelf to be a vile ſinner &amp; miſerable wretch, and he would fain quench the light, rather then obey it, but there is his condemnation, for the light will find him out, if he hide himſelf never ſo cloſely in his own conceits, and thoughts, by his carnall reaſon and falne wiſdom, and the wo will follow him, go where he will; this light will not have union with the corrupt nature, nor with man, whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt he is one with that nature, but the light will check and reprove him both in ſecret, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly, and be a teſtimony againſt ſin eternally, and alſo againſt him that is one with the evil, this light will leave all naturall men without excuſe, that they can have no cloak for their ſins, for it is privy to all their actions, both at home and abroad, &amp; it will not be bribed to hold its peace, but it will cry out againſt ſin and give ſentence againſt thee, that diſobeys it, be what thou wilt: This light doth not waver nor wander, but ſhewes thee thy wavering and wandering mind, and tells thee of all thy baſe actions, and if it were a naturall light, it would not ſo much oppoſe nature, and croſſe its deſire, as it doth, and will do more and more, as it doth break forth into the underſtanding, it will tell thee that thou art a naturall blind man, in the things
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:168082:10"/>of God, and it wil not be beholding to thee for all thy natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall learning and tongues, but croſſe it and thee both, and tell thee the wiſdom of the fleſh, and the world, is fooliſhneſſe with God, and the love and friendſhip of die world is enmity with God, and thou muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ye to thy own wiſdom, and naturall learning, and tongues, before thou knoweſt God indeed and in truth, this light was before the fall, and cometh forth from God, to call out of the fall again, and if thou wilt not obey it, it will condemn thee eternally, as light as thou makes of it, but it is becauſe the wilde nature is head, but thou maiſt go where thou wilt, it will not leave thee, and it will tell thee that all thy worſhips which thou ſets up in thy own will, and by thy own wiſdom, not acceptable with God, and this light will tell thee that all thy prayers are an abomination to the Lord, whilſt thou regardeſt iniquity in thy heart, this light will tell thee that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept thou be born again, thou ſhalt never inherit the kingdom of God, and when it breaketh thy peace, and raiſeth up tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in thee, for thy unrighteous actions, then thou apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the wrath of God againſt ſin in thee, thou wouldſt be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying the promiſes of the Saints conditions, which was to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother ſeed, to heal the wound in thee, when the ſeed of the ſerpent gets a blow, by the ſtroak of the righteous judgement of God; But this will confound thy wit, and muddle thy me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, and ſcatter all thy conceits and imaginations, and croſſe thy will in its expectations, &amp; tell thee thou art reprobate from God, in that nature then thou ſhalt ſee this is not a naturall light that doth ſo oppoſe and ſtrike at all naturall wayes, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, tongues learnings and vanities, it will work thee into unity with it, if you give up to be guided by it, and lead thee into eternity, but it will confute, and confound, and condemn thee, if thou do not obey it, and ſo thou art left without all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, thou naturall blind man, that lives in thy motions and high conceits, but thou art found out, and thy place of aboad, and art in <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Egyptian</hi> darkneſſe, this light ſhineth in darkneſſe, but darkneſſe comprehends it not, thou that wouldſt go about to comprehend the light of thy ſubtilty and ſerpentine wit, thou art an enemy to God, and to thy own ſoul, and thou wouldſt fain know much, that thou mighteſt have it at com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, to talk of, but thou wouldſt not put in practice, therefore thou knoweſt ſo much as will ſerve to condemn thee, For thy
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:168082:10"/>diſobedience to the light, the light will not be comprehended by thee, thou theif, thou wouldſt fain comprehend it, that thou mighteſt thereby be exalted, and thou wouldſt rob God of his glory, and take it to thy ſelf, and thou wouldſt command the light, that thou mighteſt be a Lord thy ſelf, but it ſtands out of thy reach, and it will not be commanded by thee, though thou mayſt conceive ſomething from it, and catch it to talk of, yet except thou do walk accordingly, it will tell thee thou art for deſtruction, and this light will be thy condemnation, who ever thou art that doſt not obey it, and it will ſcatter thy imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and daſh down all thy conceivings, and high motions, and tell thee thou art yet unreconciled to God, and check thee, and break thy peace, if thou do but give ear to it, it will wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for me in thy conſcience, this light is within thee,<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.9. Ioh. 8.12. Pſal. 36.9. Iſa. 49.6. Iſa. 1.60, 19. 2 Pet. 1.19. 2 Cor. 13.5. Col. 1.23.</note> it is not without, in books, nor Scriptures: The Sriptures do declare of it, but they are not the light, it is within, and ſprings from a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine root, and thou canſt not comprehend it, therefore wait up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God, in obedience to it, and it will teach thee, and ſhew thee the way to ſalvation, and the way to condemnation, and ſet before thee life and death, good and evil, chuſe thee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou wilt join to, if thou join with the good ſeed, thou wilt find power againſt ſin, to withſtand the evil, and it will judge and break down wickedneſſe in thee, and ſlay the ſeed of the ſerpent, and adminiſter to that which is captivated through the luſt, and raiſe it up, that thou may worſhip with it a God near hand, and as the ſeed of God doth ariſe in thee, it will open parrables and dark ſayings, and bring every ſecret thing to judgement in thee, and the ſeed being raiſed up by the power of the Lord, to rule over the deceit, it will not bend to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell, if he would give it all the world, one ſeed raiſed up out of one grave, by one power, and brought into one covenant, baptized by one ſpirit into one body, though ten times ten thouſand in particulars, yet they are but one in the body, one faith, one ſeed, one baptizing, one ſupper, one covenant, one God and father, all one heart, and one ſoul, ſerving God in one way, worſhipping him in the ſpirit, and with one mouth, all glorifying his great and glorious name, and who are of this ſeed, are of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and where it is carryed up into power, it will tread upon the ſeed of the ſerpent, and ſtrike at the head of it, where ever it ſees it, who are of the ſeed of the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:168082:11"/>ſerpent are one, though ten hundred thouſand, and are in uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with the deceit, the beaſt and falſe prophet, and in the falſe worſhips, worſhipping the works of their hands, and the ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations of their own hearts, and they are acted and guided by the power of the Divell, but they ſhall drink of the wine of the wrath of God powred out without mixture, and be tormented night and day. <hi>Rev.</hi> 14 9, 10, 11. and all that ſeed ſhall be ſhut out, and ſhall never enter into the city of the living God, but death and hell ſhall be caſt into the lake of fire, this is the ſecond death; and whoſoever is not found written in the Lambs book of life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> muſt be caſt into the lake of fire. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20 14, 15. and the ſeed of the ſerpent never was, nor never ſhall be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the book of life, and thoſe that are joined with that ſeed, are one, and ſhall never enter into the holy city: for the ſeed of God, and the ſeed of the ſerpent have enmity placed betwixt them, and they can never be reconciled together, and that which defileth ſhall not enter, for without is all that ſeed caſt, and is reprobate from God, and muſt not enter into the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.8. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.15.</p>
               <p>Bleſſed are they that do his commands, that they may have right to the tree of life, and enter into the city, through the ſtraight way. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.14. he that overcometh ſhall inherit all things, and I will be his God, and he ſhall be my ſon. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.7.</p>
               <p>This ſeed where it hath overcome through the power and ſtrength of the Lord, and is ſet above, it doth comprehend all languages<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> kindreds, and tongues, and all <hi>BabyIons</hi> wayes and worſhips, and doth triumph and rejoyce over them all, and ſees where the Antechiſts and deceivers all are, and from whence they all come, and whither they ſhall return again.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:168082:11"/>
               <head>The <hi>Ranters Principles,</hi> and deniall of them by us.</head>
               <p>ON the firſt day of the ſeventh moneth, we met with one <hi>Robert Wilkinſon</hi> of <hi>Coaton</hi> in <hi>Leiſterſhire,</hi> and he ſaid he was born of God, and could not commit ſin, and ſaid he was both God and the Devill, and he ſaid there was no God but him, nor no Devill but him, and he ſaid whom he bleſt was bleſt, and whom he curſt was curſt, and he ſaid he was a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and ſo he is, he ſaid the Apoſtles were lyars and deceivers and I gave him a Bible to prove that, and he ſaid die Bible was a pack of lyes, and there was neither heaven nor hell but here, and yet he was both in heaven and in hell, and he had as lieve be in hell, as in heaven, and he ſaid he was a ſerpent, and a whoremaſter, and before he ſaid he was born of God, and could not commit ſin. Now all that are in the light may ſee this confuſion, and this Beaſt is full of blaſphemy, and the ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance of God he ſhall not nor cannot eſcape. Wo to the Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, this book is as a teſtimony againſt you, from us whom the world calls Quakers, and you and your wicked principles we deny, and hold them and you accurſed. <hi>GaI.</hi> 1.9.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtles were not as many that did corrupt the word of God, but were of ſincerity, and in the light of God ſpake they in Chriſt. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.17. and he was no lyar nor deceiver, though the wicked ones counted him one, <hi>Joh.</hi> 7. as thou wicked one doſt, and the Apoſtles were not lyars, and decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers as thou <hi>Wilkinſon</hi> Ranter ſaid they were. The world cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them deceivers, and counted them deceivers, as I told thee, yet they were true, though counted deceivers by ſuch as thou art, the Apoſtles were the Ambaſſadours of Chriſt, and they pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the <hi>Corinthians</hi> in Chriſts ſtead to be reconciled to God. 2 <hi>Cor</hi> 5.20. and Chriſt was no lyar, nor no guile was found in his mouth, and they were without guile as he was. <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.5. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.6, 7, 8. <hi>Pev.</hi> 18.20. But thou <hi>Wilkinſon,</hi> and you Ranters, falſe Apoſtles, are full of guile and deceit, that ſayes the Apoſtles of Chriſt were lyars and deceivers, when firſt they were Chriſts Ambaſſadours, and ſecondly they were work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers together with him, and he did not work in the iniquity as
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:168082:12"/>you Ranters do, for they in all things prove themſelves as the miniſters of God. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11.2.7. which thou <hi>Wilkinſon</hi> and you Ranters are enemies unto, thirdly, they had wounded the hidden things of diſhoneſty, and did not walk in craftineſſe. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12. as thou <hi>Wilkinſon</hi> and you Ranters do, and fourthly, they were a ſweet favour of Chriſt, with them that were ſaved. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.15. but thou <hi>Wilkinſon</hi> and you Ranters ſtinks, and are an ill ſavour amongſt them that walk with the dogs, ſorcerers and liars. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.15.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wilkinſon,</hi> of a God thou art born with, but thy God as I told thee before, is the God of the world, that hath blinded the mind and the minds of all you Ranters, wicked ones, and from them the Goſpell is hid as it is written. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.3, 4. and that God that is of the world and the Devill is one, which is the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that begat thee, and all the generation of lyars and luſtfull ones, ſuch as thou art. <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.44. and the ſerpent thou art a whoremaſter as thou ſaidſt, and art in the myſtery of <hi>Babylon,</hi> committing fornication,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.9, 10. Gal. 5.10, 20, 21. Rev. 20.15. Rev. 21.27.</note> and art full of the filthyneſſe thereof. <hi>Rev.</hi> 15. thou beaſt that carryeth the whore, ſhall go with her into perdition, and all whoremongers and adulterers God will judge, and the ſerpent thou art, and you Ranters, Scorpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Serpents, you ſhall not eſcape the damnation of hell. <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.33. for heaven thou haſt nothing to do to talk of, who hath no part nor portion in it, for the lake thou art, and the tormentor thou ſhalt know, as <hi>Dives</hi> did, and thou wiuck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed one, and you wicked Ranters, and the wicked, and all that forgot God ſhall be turned into hell. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.17. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25, 41. with the light are you ſeen, and all thy crooked wayes, thou crooked ſerpent, with the light comprehended, and with the light for ever condemned, and all the Gods of the heathen ſhall be famiſhed.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
